<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>gaussian on Jarvist Moore Frost</title>
    <link>https://jarvist.github.io/tags/gaussian/</link>
    <description>Recent content in gaussian on Jarvist Moore Frost</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2012--2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2014 13:35:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jarvist.github.io/tags/gaussian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian: add &#39;Density=Current&#39; for post-HF</title>
      <link>https://jarvist.github.io/post/gaussian-add-densitycurrent-for-post-hf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2014 13:35:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jarvist.github.io/post/gaussian-add-densitycurrent-for-post-hf/</guid>
      <description>Do your electrostatics / population analysis from some expensive post-HartreeFock calculation look suspiciously similar to the HF result? You probably forgot to add &amp;lsquo;Density=Current&amp;rsquo; to your input stack.
I don&amp;rsquo;t understand why this isn&amp;rsquo;t the default, as when you are doing (hybrid)DFT calculations, the SCF density is being varied, thus the pop / electrostatics output change with functional.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple oligomer conformer calculation </title>
      <link>https://jarvist.github.io/post/simple-oligomer-conformer-calculation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2013 14:48:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jarvist.github.io/post/simple-oligomer-conformer-calculation/</guid>
      <description>I was moaning to a PhD student in the group about the perennial issue of checking representative torsional conformers of oligomers. In this case it was the question about whether you&amp;rsquo;d see a large variation in oscillator strength (of a TDDFT calculation) if you change the conformation (we don&amp;rsquo;t see a big variation in the energies of excited states, unless you break conjugation). This is a genuine issue as the potential energy barrier for these torsional variations are thermally accessible, and typically presents at least two local minima (head-tail and head-head), if not 4 minima (where the flat alignments are sterically hindered), so real polymers will be sampling at least some of these structures.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>