<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Jarvist Moore Frost: Academic blog</title>
    <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Jarvist Moore Frost: Academic blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 14:44:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://jarvist.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Delta SCF: Calculating work functions of molecular electronic materials</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/2016-03-17-delta-scf/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2016 14:44:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/2016-03-17-delta-scf/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A key issue in the design of functional electronic materials is the alignment
of energy levels.
This enables the creation of selective contacts, essential to make
active electronic components.
The key metric is the Electron Affinity (energy gain by adding an electron from
infinite distance) and Ionisation Potential (energy required to remove an
electron from the bulk to infinite distance).
In a metal there is no distinction between these values (the same energy state
is involved), and both are equivalent to the Work Function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When calculating electronic structure, in a periodic system (where the
electronic states are broadened bands) we talk of the Conduction Band Minimum
(CBM) and Valence Band Maximum (VBM); in a molecular system (where for
calculation we usually have an isolated molecule in vacuum) we talk in terms of
the Lowest Unoccupied Molecular Orbital (LUMO) and Highest Occupied Molecular
Orbital (HOMO).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference (in energy) between CBM and VBM, or similar LUMO and HOMO, gives
us the Fundamental Gap.
In a periodic system, this fundamental gap is a good estimate for the optical
Band Gap of the material.
This is because the absorption of a photo generates very loosly (negligably)
bound electron and hole states (the exciton).
In a molecular system, this difference between the Fundamental and Band Gap
(the exciton binding energy), can easily be 1 eV.
Methods that explicitly treat the electron-hole interaction (such as
Time-Dependent Density-Functional-Theory) are a much better estimate for the
band gap in such systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what are these orbital energies relative to?
The naive expectation would be to the vacuum energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a periodic calculation this can&amp;rsquo;t be, as there is no absolute reference in
the periodic summations used to get the electrostatic potential.
Often codes practically pin these values against the core states of the
composite atoms used in the pseudo potential - so they &amp;lsquo;look&amp;rsquo; about right, but
woe betide anyone using these as actual work functions!
However, you can define a &amp;lsquo;vacuum&amp;rsquo; region in your simulation where no electrons
are present and use the electrostatic potential in this region as the reference
for your bulk values.
My colleague Keith Butler has developed this method into a useful (and fun!)
code named MacroDensity ([1] - &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/WMD-group/MacroDensity&#34;&gt;https://github.com/WMD-group/MacroDensity&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With non-periodic (molecular) calculations, you do have an absolute
reference - the vacuum is everywhere around you!
But are the electron eigenvalues (i.e. HOMO / LUMO) actually what you want?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key thing to remember is that the Density Functional Approximation is
guaranteed to give you one thing - total energy.
The Kohn-Sham eigenvectors [2] are auxillary functions to enable the solving for
the total energy of the system, in particular by providing orbitals which can
be used to evaluate the kinetic energy of the electrons.
The debate about whether the Kohn-Sham eigenvalues have any greater meaning has
rumbled on for decades.
It has become an almost ecumenical matter.
It is usually referred to as &amp;ldquo;Koopmans&amp;rsquo; Theorem&amp;rdquo; in the literature, which
refers to the exact agreement in Hartree-Fock theory between the occupied
orbitals and the ionisation energies (energetic cost to remove an electron).
Depending on who you ask, this theory is correct for Hybrid Density Functional
Theory for: all occupied and unoccupied orbitals, just the occupied orbitals,
just the higest occupied orbital (HOMO).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly in my testing with organic electron materials and hybrid density
functionals, the HOMO often seems a good estimate for the ionisation potential.
The LUMO is often not even correlated with variations in electron affinity
(i.e. it is qualitatively and quantitatively wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if we don&amp;rsquo;t trust our single-electron eigenvalues, what can we do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A conceptually (and practically!) simple method is that of the &amp;lsquo;Delta SCF&amp;rsquo;.
The name is rather curious, but it seems to have stuck.
You calculate the total Self-Consistent-Field energy of a &lt;code&gt;N&lt;/code&gt; electron system,
and deduct the total energy of a &lt;code&gt;N+1&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;N-1&lt;/code&gt;) system.
This difference is the total energy upon adding (or removing) an electron, and
is therefore the Electron Affinity (or Ionisation Energy).
You do this at the geometry of the neutral molecule (apart from anything else,
this stops the difference in total energy requiring consideration of the
nuclear-nuclear repulsion which would change between two different geometries).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As ever in electronic structure theory this method &amp;lsquo;weighs the admiral by weighing
the battleship with and without him on board&amp;rsquo;.
It is thus extremely important that errors in the two total energies are
carefully controlled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative, which chemists seem to particularly like, is to estimate the
Ionisation Potential from the HOMO of a DFT calculation, and then add on the
Band Gap of the material via a TDDFT calculation to get the Electron Affinity.
It is somewhat surprising that this often gives a good agreement to the solid
state energies.
One possibility is that it represents some kind of &amp;lsquo;Pauling point&amp;rsquo; (correct for
the wrong reasons), that the exciton binding energy (and assorted systematic
errors) in the TDDFT is somehow compensating for the delocalisation of the
wavefunction in a solid, and the effect of the dielectric environment.
This method I used in a 2009 study of various fullerene adduct isomers [3].
Later work (alas unpublished) on a much wider range of fullerenes suggested
that the major variation in the Electron Affinity (~LUMO) was due to there
being a constant Fundamental Gap between it and the HOMO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Casida (yes, that Casida!) has some interesting slides on why there should
be such an agreement between TDDFT and Delta-SCF [4].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;doing-it-for-real-with-gaussian:fbce3db7e066d2ec23c5af7d0bd6b47a&#34;&gt;Doing it for real with Gaussian&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you want to do a Delta-SCF calculation for a molecule-in-vacuum with Gaussian.
You start with a carefully converged single point calculation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#p sp b3lyp/6-31g* SCF(Tight,Conver=8) Integral(Grid=UltraFine)

Neutral calculation - for Delta-SCF.

0 1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A standard, single point, energy calculation, with upped convergence &amp;amp; the
two-electron integrals calculated on an ultrafine grid. The &lt;code&gt;0 1&lt;/code&gt; is the
&lt;code&gt;Charge Multiplicity&lt;/code&gt;. This is a Neutral (Charge=0) calculation in a spin Singlet
(Multiplicity=1) configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have made the convergence tighter (i.e. it will do more SCF cycles to get
a lower noise answer) on an increased fidelity integration grid. See:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gaussian.com/g_tech/g_ur/k_integral.htm&#34;&gt;http://www.gaussian.com/g_tech/g_ur/k_integral.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now the same structure (no further nuclear relaxation), as a charged doublet.
If you want the energy of adding an electron to the &amp;lsquo;LUMO&amp;rsquo; (the electron
affinity), you compare the neutral energy to the system with an added electron
(Charge=-1, the Anion). This is comparing &lt;code&gt;N&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;N+1&lt;/code&gt; electrons.
For a Delta-SCF calculation of the Ionisation Potentail (IP), you compare to
the &lt;code&gt;N-1&lt;/code&gt; electron case, the cation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#p sp b3lyp/6-31g* SCF(Tight,Conver=8) Integral(Grid=UltraFine)

Anion calculation - for Delta-SCF of the LUMO / Electron Affinity.

-1 2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is it. Now run these jobs, calculate the difference of the total SCF
energy between them, and you have your estimate of the Ionisation Potential or
the Electron Affinity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/sh
neutral=` grep &amp;quot;SCF Done&amp;quot; &amp;quot;${1}&amp;quot; | awk &#39;{print $5}&#39; `
charged=` grep &amp;quot;SCF Done&amp;quot; &amp;quot;${2}&amp;quot; | awk &#39;{print $5}&#39; `

echo -n &amp;quot;${1}    &amp;quot;
echo -n &amp;quot;($neutral - $charged ) * 27.211&amp;quot; | bc -l
echo &amp;quot;  eV&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references:fbce3db7e066d2ec23c5af7d0bd6b47a&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Macrodensity - codes to read VASP LOCPOT files and calculate electrostatic
potential derived quantities (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/WMD-group/MacroDensity&#34;&gt;https://github.com/WMD-group/MacroDensity&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] Kohn, Walter; Sham, Lu Jeu (1965). &amp;ldquo;Self-Consistent Equations Including
Exchange and Correlation Effects&amp;rdquo;. Physical Review 140 (4A): A1133–A1138 (&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRev.140.A1133&#34;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/PhysRev.140.A1133&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] Frost, J. M., Faist, M. A. and Nelson, J. (2010), Energetic Disorder in
Higher Fullerene Adducts: A Quantum Chemical and Voltammetric Study. Adv.
Mater., 22: 4881–4884. &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/adma.201002189&#34;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/adma.201002189&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] Mark Casida - Reconciling Delta-SCF and TDDFT, Transparencies from a talk, 1999
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://online.kitp.ucsb.edu/online/tddft-c99/casida/oh/01.html&#34;&gt;http://online.kitp.ucsb.edu/online/tddft-c99/casida/oh/01.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello HUGO!</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/2016-03-11-hello-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2016 22:44:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/2016-03-11-hello-hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This blog used to be on wordpress, at
&lt;a href=&#34;https://jarvistmoorefrost.wordpress.com&#34;&gt;https://jarvistmoorefrost.wordpress.com&lt;/a&gt;.
( There are a few comments by other people scattered amongst those posts, I&amp;rsquo;m
not sure how to best transfer / archive these. )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Files were extracted to a plain text Markdown
format, and are now published with &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; with the
&lt;code&gt;nofancy&lt;/code&gt; theme (slightly tweaked). I moved this blog from wordpress as I had
grown irritated with the editing experience, and I hope that being able to edit
and push from the command line would get me blogging more regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time will see.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talks and Seminars at Bath University</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/2015-12-08-talks-and-seminars-at-bath-university/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2015 14:16:34 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/2015-12-08-talks-and-seminars-at-bath-university/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are a number of groups at Bath University doing work of interest to
Condensed Matter Theorists. This is just a quick set of &amp;lsquo;hot links&amp;rsquo; to the
individual seminar sites + pages. It is not intended to be exhaustive or
complete, but I try and see what&amp;rsquo;s on at all of these events for every week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physics: Theory group seminars: &lt;a href=&#34;http://people.bath.ac.uk/rj248/theory_seminars.html&#34;&gt;http://people.bath.ac.uk/rj248/theory_seminars.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maths: General colloquium, Landscapes in Mathematical Sciences: &lt;a href=&#34;http://people.bath.ac.uk/masgks/Landscapes/&#34;&gt;http://people.bath.ac.uk/masgks/Landscapes/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maths: Numerical Analysis group seminars: &lt;a href=&#34;http://people.bath.ac.uk/em459/NASeminar/naseminar.html&#34;&gt;http://people.bath.ac.uk/em459/NASeminar/naseminar.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physics: Nanoseminars: &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.bath.ac.uk/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=75175127&#34;&gt;https://wiki.bath.ac.uk/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=75175127&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embarrassing embarrassingly parallel</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/embarrassing-embarrassingly-parallelism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2015 21:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/embarrassing-embarrassingly-parallelism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I gave up OPENMP&amp;rsquo;ing my Monte Carlo code about a year ago. I was trying to do it at the level of MC moves, and there are massive issues here in that the different threads are trying to sample and update the same simulation space - leading to segfaults as the variables crash into one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One method I&amp;rsquo;ve seen used in the literature is domain decomposition - where each thread runs MC on a segment of the simulation volume. This is quite a headache to set up, and then you have issues about simultaneous updates, and the inability to exchange particles / states across the boundaries. All scary issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I gave up. I am not a computer scientist. I could not understand even the terms of reference; Lambda calculus reductions and all that jazz. In Simon Peyton Jones&amp;rsquo; terms, &amp;ldquo;I am a worm.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I revisited it this evening, with the intention of seeing whether I could separate the thread of the random number generator at least. However, it instantaneously struct me what I should do. Each MC-move attempt calls &amp;lsquo;site-energy&amp;rsquo; with the test move which has a set of for loops evaluating over nearby space (i.e. with a cutoff) to get a total energy change for the test move.
The change in energy variable &amp;lsquo;dE&amp;rsquo; is a natural reduction vector, none of this modifies the simulation volume, and in a production run where you are integrating out a large volume of space for accurate energies - the majority of computer time is spend in these for loops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One: &lt;code&gt;#pragma omp parallel for reduction(+:dE)&lt;/code&gt; before the start of the for-loop nest; and a recompile with &lt;code&gt;-fopenmp&lt;/code&gt;, and it now maxes out the 4 hyperthreaded cores on my laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scaling will be more limited on bigger machines, and increase in speed will only be seen where this energy summation, rather than the single-core modifications to the simulation volume and random number generator, dominate the CPU required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But still. Embarrassing embarrassingly parallel, because I could have and should have seen this a year ago!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Organising computational job workflow, as you go: freck</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/organising-computational-job-workflow-as-you-go-freck/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2015 16:15:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/organising-computational-job-workflow-as-you-go-freck/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The workflow in computational materials modelling is often highly complex, and bespoke to the particular calculations you are doing. The flow is highly derivative (results of later jobs depend on work on prior jobs), but can also be quite chaotic and multiply branching. Unsurprisingly, your files easily end up very messy, with significant confusion about what steps were required to get to the present working setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Version control is an absolute godsend, being able to flow down the list settings changes is extremely useful, and then being able to simply open the Git archive on GitHub as a way of archiving your research data is fantastic. However, this still leaves problems to be solved - the main one is actually constructing the folder structure sensibly. (A lesser issue is that intermediate and binary files in electronic structure calculations can be enormous (&amp;gt;multi gigabyte) and so far too large for git.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To aid this I&amp;rsquo;ve written a very lightweight shell script called &amp;lsquo;freck&amp;rsquo; (to move swiftly or nimbly, an obsolete English word). Each time this is run in a working directory, it generates a folder named 0001-, 0002- etc. with a user-requested file name, and then moves all the present working files into that directory. It also saves a &amp;lsquo;breadcrumb&amp;rsquo; file with information about when and where you are writing this. I would like it to also add information extracted from your present history (i.e. all the commands you have used to work on the data), but the problem is that the shell script runs within its own shell, and it&amp;rsquo;s not obvious how to easily or portably access this.
(history &amp;gt; history.log ; is very quick to run though)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The suggestion would be that you then typically run a &amp;lsquo;git add&amp;rsquo; on the small input / output files, and commit these to a repository with a sensible commit history.
Then copy the necessary files to continue your job into the PWD, and continue work.
But it&amp;rsquo;s flexible enough that you can also just use this to separate your work when running on a cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure I&amp;rsquo;m not the only one who&amp;rsquo;s ended up with a folder structure that ends up looking hellishly like this:-
~/PROJECT_FOO/geom_opt/geom_opt_restart/geom_opt_restart_higher_convergence/moar_kpoints/cation_geom/cation_geom_restart/frequency_calc/ etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead you end up with something much more sensible, time ordered and single-depthh: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jarvist/CDFT-C2H4&#34;&gt;https://github.com/jarvist/CDFT-C2H4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, check it out here + I&amp;rsquo;m always interested in all + any feedback!
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jarvist/freck&#34;&gt;https://github.com/jarvist/freck&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing scientific papers</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/writing-scientific-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 22:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/writing-scientific-papers/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;(Updated 2016-03-12 to re-add the links)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am probably the last person you would want to consult on tips to write
a scientific publication. I&amp;rsquo;m slow, I procrastinate, my English is not the
best, much work lies on the cutting room floor - skeletons of half assembled
papers. Still, &amp;lsquo;that which we are, we are&amp;rsquo;, though my skills are lacking I&amp;rsquo;m
very interested in improving, and certainly enjoy reading a well written paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an unfortunate fact that the quality of scientific writing is
decreasing as a function of time.
Some of this can be explained by the laudable continuing expansion of
scienitific research across the world resulting in a greater number of authors
writing English as an additional language.
I believe the major reason stems from the unrelenting pressure to publish.
Many more papers are written, yet there are still only the same number of days
in the year.
With these publication metrics deciding so much of our future careers (and thus
lives), there is also enormous pressure to &amp;lsquo;glam up&amp;rsquo; work and oversell, as well
as to &amp;lsquo;salami slice&amp;rsquo; and represent work that belongs together in one
paper in many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be that scientists would work continuously on a problem, and then
publish when a &amp;lsquo;breakthrough&amp;rsquo; had been made.
To be honest I think we would have a better scientific corpus if this was still
the case - careful work on a hard problem for a few years until we gain some
traction, then write it up for the benefit of anyone who could take it
elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Along these lines, Ross McKenzie has a recent blog post &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://condensedconcepts.blogspot.co.uk/2015/02/in-praise-of-modest-goals.html&#34;&gt;In praise of modest
goals&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the first thing to do when writing is to overcome the cynicism!
When I get particular disaffected I return to Simon Peyton Jones&amp;rsquo; talk on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g3dkRsTqdDA&#34;&gt;how
to write a great research paper&lt;/a&gt;
. His enthusiasm and motivation is infectious. I am a worm. A worm with
a infectious mind virus, and that is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabine Hossenfelder wrote a useful blog post on &lt;a href=&#34;http://backreaction.blogspot.co.uk/2015/01/how-to-write-your-first-scientific-paper.html&#34;&gt;How to write your first
scientific
paper&lt;/a&gt;,
this covers the construction and sectioning of a physics paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve personally found the Penguin Writer&amp;rsquo;s Manual very useful for the nitty
gritty of &amp;lsquo;that&amp;rsquo; vs &amp;lsquo;which&amp;rsquo;. I&amp;rsquo;ve also read Strunk and White (The elements of
style), though I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how much I took from it. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://backreaction.blogspot.co.uk/2015/01/how-to-write-your-first-scientific-paper.html&#34;&gt;economist style
guide&lt;/a&gt;
(available online) is also very useful as a reference.
(2016 update: Steven Pinker&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;The Sense of Style&amp;rsquo; is fantastic. Dispels a lot
of prescriptive myths, but also teaches how to analyse your sentences and
identify clumsy phrases.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I much prefer to write with Latex. Sometimes I first go via Markdown (a
lightweight markup language that looks a lot like how you would naturally
format a text email), so I don&amp;rsquo;t need to bother with thinking about the Latex
commands when forming a text, and then convert to Latex (with pandoc) for
inclusions of figures &amp;amp; all the revisions that incur thereafter. The whole
project I put within a &amp;lsquo;git&amp;rsquo; repository and so have version control,
effectively offsite backup (to Github / Bitbucket). To get the diffs to work
well with the files, it&amp;rsquo;s easiest to add a newline after the end of every
sentence (I usually hard-break my lines at 80 chars as I write in Vim).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have contributed to papers in Microsoft Word (usually originating with
collaborators). It works OK, and the track changes / comment tool can be really
useful, though a distressing number of collaborators seem to send you back
a &amp;lsquo;clean&amp;rsquo; document with the tracking dropped. Whether that&amp;rsquo;s due to ignorance
of the tools, compatibility with different versions of Word, or an attempt to
bury any information about which of your changes they reverted, I do not know.
Certainly it makes me respect them less both academically and professionally.
It is most incredibly frustrating to be editing a sentence, not sure
whether you&amp;rsquo;re applying the same change again, undoing an important correction
or what.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I typically plot data in GNUPLOT or XMGRACE, sometimes also in Python&amp;rsquo;s
Matplotlib (though this is much less deterministic - the output depends on the
specific version you have installed, and it can be extremely frustrating to
reproduce a tweaked diagram). I&amp;rsquo;ve found some useful websites on tips + tricks
for plotting, useful beyond an immediate answer to resolving a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;useful-general-resources:eef4a03bfcc260366f6af32064313cc4&#34;&gt;Useful general resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simon Peyton Jones talk &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g3dkRsTqdDA&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g3dkRsTqdDA&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hacker News discussion &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6989806&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6989806&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sabine Hossenfelder blogpost
&lt;a href=&#34;http://backreaction.blogspot.co.uk/2015/01/how-to-write-your-first-scientific-paper.html&#34;&gt;http://backreaction.blogspot.co.uk/2015/01/how-to-write-your-first-scientific-paper.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Researcher&amp;rsquo;s Bible
&lt;a href=&#34;http://homepages.inf.ed.ac.uk/bundy/how-tos/resbible.html&#34;&gt;http://homepages.inf.ed.ac.uk/bundy/how-tos/resbible.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Economist - Style Guide &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.economist.com/styleguide/introduction&#34;&gt;http://www.economist.com/styleguide/introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;colour:eef4a03bfcc260366f6af32064313cc4&#34;&gt;Colour&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IBM paper &amp;ldquo;Why should engineers and scientists be worried about color?&amp;rdquo;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.research.ibm.com/people/l/lloydt/color/color.HTM&#34;&gt;http://www.research.ibm.com/people/l/lloydt/color/color.HTM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adobe&amp;rsquo;s Color CC &lt;a href=&#34;https://color.adobe.com/explore/most-popular/?time=all&#34;&gt;https://color.adobe.com/explore/most-popular/?time=all&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TIGERcolor, Introduction to color theory
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tigercolor.com/color-lab/color-theory/color-theory-intro.htm&#34;&gt;http://www.tigercolor.com/color-lab/color-theory/color-theory-intro.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smashing Magazine, Color theory for designers
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2010/02/color-theory-for-designer-part-3-creating-your-own-color-palettes/&#34;&gt;https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2010/02/color-theory-for-designer-part-3-creating-your-own-color-palettes/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colorbrewer &lt;a href=&#34;http://colorbrewer2.org/&#34;&gt;http://colorbrewer2.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;writing:eef4a03bfcc260366f6af32064313cc4&#34;&gt;Writing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20 Obsolete English Words
&lt;a href=&#34;http://matadornetwork.com/abroad/20-obsolete-english-words-that-should-make-a-comeback/&#34;&gt;http://matadornetwork.com/abroad/20-obsolete-english-words-that-should-make-a-comeback/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;University of Manchester academic phrasebank &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.phrasebank.manchester.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;http://www.phrasebank.manchester.ac.uk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uni of Illinois, Captilisation and dashes in Physics (PDF)
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nt.ntnu.no/users/haugwarb/Misc/capitalization.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.nt.ntnu.no/users/haugwarb/Misc/capitalization.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Marsh, 10 grammar rules to forget
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2013/sep/30/10-grammar-rules-you-can-forget&#34;&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2013/sep/30/10-grammar-rules-you-can-forget&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;plotting:eef4a03bfcc260366f6af32064313cc4&#34;&gt;Plotting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Xmgrace tips &lt;a href=&#34;http://lptms.u-psud.fr/wiki/index.php/Tips_for_Xmgrace&#34;&gt;http://lptms.u-psud.fr/wiki/index.php/Tips_for_Xmgrace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Grace/Inkscape workflow
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/patrickbwarren/beautiful-figures&#34;&gt;https://sites.google.com/site/patrickbwarren/beautiful-figures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grace Forum &lt;a href=&#34;http://plasma-gate.weizmann.ac.il/Grace/phpbb/&#34;&gt;http://plasma-gate.weizmann.ac.il/Grace/phpbb/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gnuplot Tricks &lt;a href=&#34;http://gnuplot-tricks.blogspot.co.uk/&#34;&gt;http://gnuplot-tricks.blogspot.co.uk/&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publication quality example
&lt;a href=&#34;http://gnuplot-tricks.blogspot.co.uk/2009/05/gnuplot-tricks-many-say-that-it-is.html&#34;&gt;http://gnuplot-tricks.blogspot.co.uk/2009/05/gnuplot-tricks-many-say-that-it-is.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gnuplotting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnuplotting.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.gnuplotting.org/&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Output terminals &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnuplotting.org/output-terminals/&#34;&gt;http://www.gnuplotting.org/output-terminals/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gnuplot-colorbrewer &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/aschn/gnuplot-colorbrewer&#34;&gt;https://github.com/aschn/gnuplot-colorbrewer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;git-latex-markdown:eef4a03bfcc260366f6af32064313cc4&#34;&gt;Git / Latex / Markdown&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Word by word diffs in Git
&lt;a href=&#34;https://idnotfound.wordpress.com/2009/05/09/word-by-word-diffs-in-git/&#34;&gt;https://idnotfound.wordpress.com/2009/05/09/word-by-word-diffs-in-git/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A call for scholarly markdown
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2012/12/13/a-call-for-scholarly-markdown/&#34;&gt;http://blogs.plos.org/mfenner/2012/12/13/a-call-for-scholarly-markdown/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CodeCogs LaTeX equation editor (useful for talks not in LaTeX Beamer!)
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.codecogs.com/latex/eqneditor.php&#34;&gt;http://www.codecogs.com/latex/eqneditor.php&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detexify - draw a symbol, find the Latex
&lt;a href=&#34;http://detexify.kirelabs.org/classify.html&#34;&gt;http://detexify.kirelabs.org/classify.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LaTeX Templates &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.latextemplates.com/&#34;&gt;http://www.latextemplates.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TikZ example &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.texample.net/tikz/examples/membrane-surface/&#34;&gt;http://www.texample.net/tikz/examples/membrane-surface/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top four LaTeX mistakes
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.johndcook.com/blog/2010/02/15/top-latex-mistakes/&#34;&gt;http://www.johndcook.com/blog/2010/02/15/top-latex-mistakes/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Precise positioning in LaTeX Beamer
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.helsinki.fi/smsiltan/2012/10/12/precise-positioning-in-latex-beamer/&#34;&gt;http://blogs.helsinki.fi/smsiltan/2012/10/12/precise-positioning-in-latex-beamer/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Papercore summaries
&lt;a href=&#34;http://papercore.org/summaries&#34;&gt;http://papercore.org/summaries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making a poster with Inkscape
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.felixbreuer.net/2010/10/24/poster.html&#34;&gt;http://blog.felixbreuer.net/2010/10/24/poster.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ambient-music-for-headphones-in-noisy-offices:eef4a03bfcc260366f6af32064313cc4&#34;&gt;Ambient music for headphones in noisy offices&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Music to let you concentrate &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5872414&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5872414&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Headphone Commute - electronic, ambient &lt;a href=&#34;http://reviews.headphonecommute.com/&#34;&gt;http://reviews.headphonecommute.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hex Grids</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/hex-grids/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2015 23:06:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/hex-grids/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Solid state materials pack together in a myriad of ways. The crystal structures are typically referred to with the name of the archetype compound. This ranges from fairly common English words such as &amp;lsquo;diamond&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;rock-salt&amp;rsquo; to, &amp;lsquo;zinc-blend&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;wurtzite&amp;rsquo; and, of course, &amp;lsquo;perovskite&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The atomic packing within these structures is fully described by their space-group, of which there are 230 to choose from. These space groups take the crystallographic (periodic structure) compatible point groups, and combine them with different possible lattice vectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://img.chem.ucl.ac.uk/sgp/large/sgp.htm&#34;&gt;http://img.chem.ucl.ac.uk/sgp/large/sgp.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some structures are fiendishly complicated, others are effectively cubic grids (perhaps with lattice vectors which are neither orthogonal nor equal in length). Even very complicated structures often have a sub lattice which packs cubically, or with hexagonal close packing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the perhaps surprising things is that hexagonal packing and cubic packing are extremely similar to one other - in particular cubic (BCC and FCC) and hexagonal close packing both have a coordination number of 12. Each sphere (atom) has 12 nearest neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very useful, when you are building a computer model for a large structure. You can store the data about site occupancy in a simple array[][][], and calculate various necessary metrics (in particular real space distance vectors) via simple (i.e. free, in terms of computer time) arithmetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came across an article on hexagonal grids today; much of it was startling familiar, but in that way that it was giving you a framework and lexicon for understanding for what you&amp;rsquo;d hacked together with a partial glimpse of true understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(It&amp;rsquo;s written from the perspective of a games developer, but it&amp;rsquo;s directly applicable to scientific computation - just don&amp;rsquo;t tell the Research Councils how similar our austere science is to a game engine!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.redblobgames.com/grids/hexagons/&#34;&gt;http://www.redblobgames.com/grids/hexagons/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;via HN discussion &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8941588&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8941588&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snippet: SSH at Bath Uni</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/snippet-ssh-at-bath-uni/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2015 14:36:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/snippet-ssh-at-bath-uni/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I polished some slides I gave at our group meeting last summer, on using &amp;lsquo;ssh&amp;rsquo; proficiently at Bath university. I thought they may be of use to other&amp;rsquo;s, so published them online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They mainly cover the setting up of a ssh-config (the examples are probably useful for most people that use HPC facilities), and tunneling via the LCPU facility (fairly Bath specific, though other academic institutes might offer a similar unix machine in a DMZ to bounce through).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1OhQL_P5VT_467JhfcCVCFSmryZ0UoQkm_QzGTLNb7bU/pub?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000&#34;&gt;Google Present Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jarvist/filthy-dotfiles/blob/master/ssh-config&#34;&gt;https://github.com/jarvist/filthy-dotfiles/blob/master/ssh-config&lt;/a&gt; - my ssh-config, with Bath (&amp;amp; jarvist!) specific settings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snippet: New Julia paper from the developers</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/snippet-new-julia-paper-from-the-developers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2014 13:32:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/snippet-new-julia-paper-from-the-developers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Looks to be a great reference, with plenty of code snippets getting bits of numerical methods working, finishing on the random-matrix semicircle theory, with @parallel speedup! Wish this was around when I was figuring out my little toy model&amp;hellip; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jarvist/LongSnakeMoan/blob/master/Sturm-DoS/Sturm_Drang.jl&#34;&gt;https://github.com/jarvist/LongSnakeMoan/blob/master/Sturm-DoS/Sturm_Drang.jl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/1411.1607&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/1411.1607&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;via the ever useful, if distracting, Hacker News:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8576411&#34;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8576411&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I made a poster; 2014</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/how-i-made-a-poster-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2014 04:09:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/how-i-made-a-poster-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I made a scientific poster last week, for the first time in five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I drew it in Inkscape, a free opensource vector drawing package. I&amp;rsquo;m have quite a lot of experience using Inkscape in drawing cave surveys, but I believe it&amp;rsquo;s both relatively easy to use, and has some extremely useful tools for constructing posters (most notably the alignment &amp;amp; distribution tool). The one gotcha is that you have to explicitly ask for it to spell check your text fields! It&amp;rsquo;s native fileformat is SVG based, and it is very happy to import PDFs (i.e. figures / graphs - from gnuplot I use the colour postscript terminal, then &amp;lsquo;ps2pdf&amp;rsquo; on the command line).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jarvist/PerovskiteKinematics/raw/master/2014-10_JMF_Korea_Poster.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jarvistmoorefrost.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/poster.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Crystal Kinematics Poster&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most scientists, I am no designer. So I&amp;rsquo;m mainly winging it, and can&amp;rsquo;t rely on whether things look right or not! I found a colour scheme that was close to some of my figures from Adobe&amp;rsquo;s Color CC [1], and then put those five colours in a swatch just outside the page on the Inkscape. I put all the main text in a medium weight Futura clone, because I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days I make my talk slides in Google Present, viewing a certain slide and then selecting &amp;ldquo;Download as SVG&amp;rdquo;, opened in Inkscape as a fairly well-behaved vector images with embedded bitmaps, to then have the slide template objects deleted &amp;amp; used within the poster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also made a tie-in website, linked from a QR code (generated with a free web service) on the poster, as a place to collate links to the YouTube videos and a reprint of the poster itself.
This I generated with GitHub pages and the Flatdoc HTML/JS code [2], a lightweight and modern responsive web framework. You put the Flatdoc HTML file (template.html) as index.html on the &amp;lsquo;gh-pages&amp;rsquo; branch of your GitHub repo, having edited the HTML to set the USER/REPO/Title correctly. It then pulls down the README.md from your &amp;lsquo;master&amp;rsquo; branch of the repo, and live renders any changes on the browser. Assuming you are used to GitHub &amp;amp; have (fairly minimal) HTML/CSS abilities this is a really quick way to put together something that looks pretty acceptable. [3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I was quite pleased with how easy it is to put together something that looks acceptable. If you are interested - have a look at the Inkscape SVG &amp;amp; the structure of the github REPO. [4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&#34;https://color.adobe.com/explore/&#34;&gt;https://color.adobe.com/explore/&lt;/a&gt;
[2] &lt;a href=&#34;http://ricostacruz.com/flatdoc/&#34;&gt;http://ricostacruz.com/flatdoc/&lt;/a&gt;
[3] &lt;a href=&#34;http://jarvist.github.io/PerovskiteKinematics/&#34;&gt;http://jarvist.github.io/PerovskiteKinematics/&lt;/a&gt;
[4] &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jarvist/PerovskiteKinematics&#34;&gt;https://github.com/jarvist/PerovskiteKinematics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maximum coverage for loops; bit reversing integars</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/maximum-coverage-for-loops-bit-reversing-integars/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2014 18:44:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/maximum-coverage-for-loops-bit-reversing-integars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So I was live-plotting some results from a simulation code (written in C), which was producing results for an input parameter (in this case Temperature), over a range generated by a for loop. Pretty standard computational physics. It was clearly suboptimal watching the new dataset arrive in small, fine, increments from zero upwards; the obvious thing was to change the discretisation of the for loop &amp;amp; make it more coarse. Yet, surely there is some way to get better coverage of the dataset, like a &amp;lsquo;streaming&amp;rsquo; JPEG or GIF arriving with increasing discretisations of the blockiness?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about some mathematical function that would jump around the space with good coverage? A pseudo-random number generator with a fixed period? Some mathematical function that would map an ascending series of integers into spatial coverage? Modulus arithmetic on some prime or co-prome addition?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How about reversing the binary digits in an incrementing integer? So instead of going 0,1,2,3&amp;hellip;254,255; you would bounce around the number line: 0,128,64,192,32,160 &amp;hellip; 127,255. So it&amp;rsquo;s sort of doing a binary split of the unoccupied locations on the number line at each step. You get maximum coverage, with increasing levels of fidelity, ending up with a complete (but missorted) dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with a Bit Twiddling hack found via Stackoverflow (&lt;a href=&#34;http://graphics.stanford.edu/~seander/bithacks.html#ReverseByteWith64BitsDiv&#34;&gt;http://graphics.stanford.edu/~seander/bithacks.html#ReverseByteWith64BitsDiv&lt;/a&gt;), the totally crazy bit-shifting code (for a byte, so covering 256 values) looks like: &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/jarvist/368622717a5d3bcadfc0&#34;&gt;https://gist.github.com/jarvist/368622717a5d3bcadfc0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s pretty low level (in Python or similar, you could reorder a list, and iterate over that instead), but the result is nice! It&amp;rsquo;s almost so useful that perhaps one should write it into a mini function or macro&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snippet: Tiddlywiki for Scholars</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/snippet-tiddlywiki-for-scholars/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 12:35:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/snippet-tiddlywiki-for-scholars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This looks like it might be extremely useful for a personal knowledge base / article discussion. It&amp;rsquo;s setup more for humanities work currently (books, biographies and authors), than science (some way to import a DOI to build a paper-discussion place would be fantastic). A collaborative journal club / papercore / paper summary might also work wonderfully within here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://tw5.scholars.tiddlyspot.com/&#34;&gt;http://tw5.scholars.tiddlyspot.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snippet: Mendeley Desktop (Mac OS) failed update</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/snippet-mendeley-desktop-mac-os-failed-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2014 14:51:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/snippet-mendeley-desktop-mac-os-failed-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mendeley Desktop on my Mac at work had silently stopped working - clicking the button in Launchpad did nothing. Navigating to the directory on the shell, cd &amp;ldquo;/Applications/Mendeley\ Desktop.app/Contents/MacOS/&amp;rdquo; it appeared a prior update had broken halfway through, leaving a null file for &amp;lsquo;Mendeley Desktop&amp;rsquo;. Whoops. However there was a &amp;lsquo;Mendeley Desktop.bak&amp;rsquo;. Running this from the shell, Mendeley Desktop appeared, and then offered to update itself, this time completing successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Links from Julia Land</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/links-from-julia-land/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2014 12:36:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/links-from-julia-land/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Julia 0.3 Release Candidate 1 has quietly appeared on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://julialang.org/downloads/&#34;&gt;nightly builds page&lt;/a&gt;; release notes in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/JuliaLang/julia/blob/master/NEWS.md&#34;&gt;very active GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt; - improvements to the REPL (tab conversion of &amp;lsquo;latex maths&amp;rsquo; to unicode), and a lot of interesting linear algebra improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inaugural JuliaCon has been held, and the presentation slidedecks are already online: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/JuliaCon/presentations&#34;&gt;https://github.com/JuliaCon/presentations&lt;/a&gt;; videos are coming but the upload date has been pushed back as they are edited and transcribed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Julia users email list, there was a link published to a very interesting essay on the history of programming languages: &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups=#!topic/julia-users/T6f9hCkDW6g&#34;&gt;https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups=#!topic/julia-users/T6f9hCkDW6g&lt;/a&gt;. It ends on a very pro-Julia note!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve personally just been using Julia &amp;lsquo;for real&amp;rsquo; in preparing some data for a publication (rather than just using iJulia as a glorified unicode-capable calculator for physical identities). Here I used Julia to calculate the partition function on the fly (by Monte Carlo integration) for an arbitrary torsional potential in a polymer, then form a tight binding Hamiltonian &amp;amp; evaluate the density of states extremely quickly with the Sturm sequence method. If I hadn&amp;rsquo;t discovered Julia, I would have been trying to do this with Python, and though totally feasible I&amp;rsquo;m not sure I would have got here. You are perpetually operating at the absolute limit of your cognitive capacity in scientific theory (and for me, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty limited); the more powerful the tools you have the more you can achieve, and Julia does indeed seem a very well geared &amp;lsquo;bicycle for the mind&amp;rsquo; in scientific computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jarvist/LongSnakeMoan/blob/master/Sturm-DoS/Sturm_Drang.jl&#34;&gt;https://github.com/jarvist/LongSnakeMoan/blob/master/Sturm-DoS/Sturm_Drang.jl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Free Physics on the Internet</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/free-physics-on-the-internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 12:36:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/free-physics-on-the-internet/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This is a collection of bookmarks I&amp;rsquo;ve collected over the years of useful
online physics notes; hopefully this will be of some use to others.
My bias is as a computational physicist doing electronic structure theory for
materials modelling, so all within the remit of condensed matter theory (no
high energy physics, for instance, and nothing that would count as
&amp;lsquo;theoretical&amp;rsquo; research for the last forty years at least).
Expect little outside pedestrian quantum mechanics and statistical physics, and
the one fundamental force you can actually interact with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partially inspired by Gerard &amp;rsquo;t Hooft&amp;rsquo;s far more complete summary
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.staff.science.uu.nl/~Gadda001/goodtheorist/index.html&#34;&gt;http://www.staff.science.uu.nl/~Gadda001/goodtheorist/index.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-notes:415b107632de82fd60457d6653a32eb1&#34;&gt;Lecture Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Richard Feynman&lt;/strong&gt; (Caltech) The Feynman lectures on physics are now available
to read freely online.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.feynmanlectures.caltech.edu/&#34;&gt;http://www.feynmanlectures.caltech.edu/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lev Landau&lt;/strong&gt; (Moscow) The original theoretical minimum; Landau&amp;rsquo;s fantastic
series translated into English are available freely on the Internet archive.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/Mechanics_541&#34;&gt;https://archive.org/details/Mechanics_541&lt;/a&gt; - start with mechanics and search
around!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Tong&lt;/strong&gt; (Cambridge) has written a highly recommended series of
undergraduate (UG) notes.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.damtp.cam.ac.uk/user/tong/teaching.html&#34;&gt;http://www.damtp.cam.ac.uk/user/tong/teaching.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leonard Susskind&lt;/strong&gt; (Stanford) has a set of Youtube lectures as part of the
Stanford Continuing Studies series. I like his very clear lecture style.
The 2013 Stat Mech (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL_IkS0viawhr3HcKH607rXbVqy28W_gB7&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL_IkS0viawhr3HcKH607rXbVqy28W_gB7&lt;/a&gt;) and Advanced QM (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLcC5RwLpGl6eyNvVfAixR18_nDmsX9rh-&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLcC5RwLpGl6eyNvVfAixR18_nDmsX9rh-&lt;/a&gt;) courses I really enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accesssible
course also dovetails with the recently published books (written with Art
Friedman).
&lt;a href=&#34;http://theoreticalminimum.com/courses&#34;&gt;http://theoreticalminimum.com/courses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Richard Fitzpatrick&lt;/strong&gt; (UT Austin) offers lecture notes, including some at the
graduate level.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://farside.ph.utexas.edu/teaching.html&#34;&gt;http://farside.ph.utexas.edu/teaching.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dan Styer&lt;/strong&gt; (Oberlin) maintains a good set of Quantum-Mechanics notes on the
web including a primer of common misconceptions.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oberlin.edu/physics/dstyer/TeachQM/&#34;&gt;http://www.oberlin.edu/physics/dstyer/TeachQM/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matthew Foulkes&lt;/strong&gt; (Imperial) has a pleasingly dense and direct postgrad
course on electrons in solids - from UG Physics to DFT in 6 sections&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmth.ph.ic.ac.uk/people/m.foulkes/pdf/esolids.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.cmth.ph.ic.ac.uk/people/m.foulkes/pdf/esolids.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Kitchin&lt;/strong&gt; (Carnegie Mellon) has a set of notes on periodic DFT
calculations (with VASP) and a Python primer (with the Atomic Simulation
Environment) in doing materials modelling calculations.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://kitchingroup.cheme.cmu.edu/pycse/&#34;&gt;http://kitchingroup.cheme.cmu.edu/pycse/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://kitchingroup.cheme.cmu.edu/dft-book/&#34;&gt;http://kitchingroup.cheme.cmu.edu/dft-book/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stefan Grimme&lt;/strong&gt; (Bonn) has a great intro-to-QuantumChemistry set of notes which
bridges the gap between a QM course and the terms used in typical codes.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thch.uni-bonn.de/tc/teaching/qc2/downloads/&#34;&gt;http://www.thch.uni-bonn.de/tc/teaching/qc2/downloads/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sherrill Group&lt;/strong&gt; (Georgia Tech) have a set of notes and Youtube videos on
quantum chemistry.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://vergil.chemistry.gatech.edu/notes/index.html&#34;&gt;http://vergil.chemistry.gatech.edu/notes/index.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDDFT School&lt;/strong&gt; TDDFT school research talks; rewrite the URL with a bit of
a guess for other years!
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tddft.org/TDDFT2014/school/&#34;&gt;http://www.tddft.org/TDDFT2014/school/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tddft.org/TDDFT2010/school/&#34;&gt;http://www.tddft.org/TDDFT2010/school/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tddft.org/TDDFT2008/lectures/&#34;&gt;http://www.tddft.org/TDDFT2008/lectures/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;journal-clubs:415b107632de82fd60457d6653a32eb1&#34;&gt;Journal Clubs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Papercore is an interesting idea - produce a &amp;lsquo;super abstract&amp;rsquo; summary of
a research paper. Quite a spin-glass focus for the papers in here, where
I guess it is used as the internal journal club.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://papercore.org/summaries&#34;&gt;http://papercore.org/summaries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;books:415b107632de82fd60457d6653a32eb1&#34;&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In truth, all the best stuff is in the books; quality and presentation of the
above notes is relatively hit and miss, and more polished and complete at the
undergraduate level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physics is quite an esoteric pursuit, so unless you have access to a university
you are unlikely to be able to find much beyond the Landau/Livshitz &amp;lsquo;Course in
Theoretical Physics&amp;rsquo; and the Feynman lectures in your library.
Most physics books are horrendously expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Dover Books reissues in physics are fantastic and cheap; like
classic movies a few decades hindsight has allowed the editors to sort the
wheat from the chaff.  The Futura / Bauhaus design for the latest covers is
extremely aesthetically pleasing.
Beware that some of the books from the dawn of Quantum Theory are more there
for historical interest than utility as a textbook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://store.doverpublications.com/by-subject-physics-mathematical-and-theoretical-physics.html&#34;&gt;http://store.doverpublications.com/by-subject-physics-mathematical-and-theoretical-physics.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>