<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bookclub on Jarvist Moore Frost: Academic blog</title>
    <link>http://jarvist.github.io/categories/bookclub/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bookclub on Jarvist Moore Frost: Academic blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <atom:link href="http://jarvist.github.io/categories/bookclub/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>ICL Bookclub - Ziman Chapter 3</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/2017-01-24-icl-bookclub-ziman-chapter-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 09:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/2017-01-24-icl-bookclub-ziman-chapter-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A little update to the book club. It&amp;rsquo;s going well! We&amp;rsquo;ve decided to work our
way through John M. Ziman&amp;rsquo;s Principles of the Theory of Solids (2nd Edition).
I really like this text, as I find the style very agreeable. It&amp;rsquo;s very
conversational, in it&amp;rsquo;s best bits it feels like standing at a black-board
having something explained just to you, the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;sect; 1 introduces periodicity as the central theme of solid state physics,
showing how the translational symmetry leads to multiply periodic functions,
which then leads to Bloch&amp;rsquo;s theorem (that the energy eigenstates in a crystal
can be written as a phase-factor / plane wave). It then builds the Brillouin
zone, and introduces periodic boundary conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;sect; 2 applies this mathematical machinery to lattice vibrations (phonons).
The construction of the dynamic matrix is described, and then a simple 1D
diatomic chain is used to show how the bands split off &amp;amp; form an optical mode.
The Ewald summation is introduced as needed when reversing from the enthalpy of
formation of an ionic crystal back to the force coefficients. The van Hove
singularities in the lattice spectrum are described, as arising from inevitable
saddle-points in the potential energy surfaces. &amp;sect; 2.11 describes
phonon-phonon interactions, but at a level that may be useful to get some more
science out of calculations with phono3py and similar software, &amp;sect; 2.12
treats imperfect lattices, and show how to embed defect-force pairs as
a perturbation to the periodic dynamic matrix. These last two sections are
actually really useful for work we&amp;rsquo;re doing currently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;sect; 3 describes electron states in the material, introducing them via nearly
free electrons. Its really quite dense, and dives into the state of the art for
solving the electronic structure problem in the late 60s. It&amp;rsquo;s really nice to
see where the theory underlying most of today&amp;rsquo;s periodic electronic structure
codes comes from, but it&amp;rsquo;s also quite heavy going! For this reason we are
re-reading this chapter separately for this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some other more verbose Ziman publications in this area are given below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear Solid-State Book Clubbers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week we are reading (again) Chapter 3 of Ziman&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Principles of the theory
of solids&amp;rdquo; (2nd edition). Muffin tins, pseudo potentials, Green&amp;rsquo;s functions and
the orthogonalised plane waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 5PM level 2 in the RSM, as usual, Thurs 26th January 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional Ziman Review papers (really book chapters) that may be useful are:-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1971 - The Calculation of Bloch Functions
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0081-1947(08)60491-9&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0081-1947(08)60491-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This goes into much more detail, and is less terse than chapter 3.
It also has some of the most surreal (and beautiful!) diagrams I&amp;rsquo;ve seen in a
scientific publication:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../images/2017-01-24-icl-bookclub-ziman-chapter-3.png&#34; alt=&#34;The calculation of Bloch Functions, muffin tins.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1962 - Electrons in metals: A short guide to the Fermi surface
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1080/00107516208205311&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/00107516208205311&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This older paper can also be useful; it&amp;rsquo;s sort of a condensed form of what became the book we are reading, but presents the material from a slightly different point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ICL Bookclub</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/2017-01-04-icl-bookclub/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 12:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/2017-01-04-icl-bookclub/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Now that the Walsh group has a critical mass at Imperial College London, I am
planning to restart the Bookclub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keith Butler kicked these off in Bath with the guiding words of everyone&amp;rsquo;s
favourite German pessimist, Arthur Schopenhauer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Buying books would be a good thing if one could also buy the time to read
 them in: but as a rule the purchase of books is mistaken for the
 appropriation of their contents.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan is to do some reading &amp;amp; self-directed study of a relevant book, and
then get together at &lt;strong&gt;5PM on Thursdays&lt;/strong&gt; (in weeks when there is not an
interesting TYC seminar) to discuss and explain things to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re going to start with the first one and a half chapters of Ziman&amp;rsquo;s
solid-state book &amp;ldquo;Principles of the theory of solids&amp;rdquo;, ideally the second
edition (1971).
( There is currently 1 copy of the 2nd edition, and 3 copies of the 1st
edition, available for loan at the Central Library, Level 4 (530.41 ZIM).)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s Chapter 1: Periodic structures, reciprocal lattice, Bloch&amp;rsquo;s theorem,
Brillouin zone; and Chapter 2: Lattice Waves: Lattice dynamics, lattice sums
(Ewald), lattice specific heat and lattice spectrum (DoS). So stopping before
the diffraction + Debye waller + phonon scattering, in the second half of the
second chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll get together to discuss this at 5PM on Thursday 12th January, &lt;strong&gt;floor two
of the RSM (Dept Materials), Imperial College London.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other books which we are planning to visit in the near future are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Martin&amp;rsquo;s DFT book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Krauth&amp;rsquo;s Stat. Mech. - Algo and Computation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tinkham&amp;rsquo;s Group Theory and Quantum Mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feynman&amp;rsquo;s Statistical Mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nye&amp;rsquo;s Physical Properties of Materials by Tensors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody welcome! You certainly don&amp;rsquo;t need to do DFT to be able to, or to
benefit from, knowing the theory. (Arguably doing calculations actually gets in
the way&amp;hellip;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a discussion channel on our &amp;ldquo;Materials Discovery Network&amp;rdquo; Slack group.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mdn-uk.slack.com/messages/icl-bookclub/&#34;&gt;https://mdn-uk.slack.com/messages/icl-bookclub/&lt;/a&gt;
It&amp;rsquo;s on the &amp;lsquo;free&amp;rsquo; plan, so messages are ephemeral, but all friendly electronic structure people very welcome!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>