<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writing on Jarvist Moore Frost</title>
    <link>https://jarvist.github.io/tags/writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Writing on Jarvist Moore Frost</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2018 13:19:10 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jarvist.github.io/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A note on notes</title>
      <link>https://jarvist.github.io/post/2018-06-25-a-note-on-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2018 13:19:10 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jarvist.github.io/post/2018-06-25-a-note-on-notes/</guid>
      <description>I believe writing notes is essential for scientific research. Both for future reference, and also to provide space to think.
I develop a lot of my understanding on paper. Once I&amp;rsquo;ve read and thought a bit about a topic, I really like starting with a fresh A4 page (or double spread) and writing down pointers to everything I know about the subject, little diagrams and snippets of mathematics. This would be wholly useless for anyone else to consult, but I find makes a good jumping off place for my thoughts, and something I can return to and rework.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing scientific papers</title>
      <link>https://jarvist.github.io/post/writing-scientific-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 22:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jarvist.github.io/post/writing-scientific-papers/</guid>
      <description>(Updated 2016-03-12 to re-add the links)
I am probably the last person you would want to consult on tips to write a scientific publication. I&amp;rsquo;m slow, I procrastinate, my English is not the best, much work lies on the cutting room floor - skeletons of half assembled papers. Still, &amp;lsquo;that which we are, we are&amp;rsquo;, though my skills are lacking I&amp;rsquo;m very interested in improving, and certainly enjoy reading a well written paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to write a great research paper, Simon Peyton Jones</title>
      <link>https://jarvist.github.io/post/how-to-write-a-great-research-paper-simon-peyton-jones/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 20:43:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jarvist.github.io/post/how-to-write-a-great-research-paper-simon-peyton-jones/</guid>
      <description>Food for thought on how to structure research (Comp Sci in this case). Fundamental premise is too turn the process on it&amp;rsquo;s head, write the paper, and then go do the work. Do watch the YouTube; he&amp;rsquo;s a great lecturer!
&amp;ldquo;Most days you think &amp;lsquo;I am a worm&amp;rsquo;. This is the natural state of the researcher.&amp;rdquo;
Youtube talk (35 mins) | Slides PDF | HN Discussion
 </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>