<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bath University on Jarvist Moore Frost: Academic blog</title>
    <link>http://jarvist.github.io/tags/bath-university/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bath University on Jarvist Moore Frost: Academic blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2013 19:03:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://jarvist.github.io/tags/bath-university/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Goodbye London; Hello Bath</title>
      <link>http://jarvist.github.io/post/goodbye-london-hello-bath/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2013 19:03:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://jarvist.github.io/post/goodbye-london-hello-bath/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the start of November 2013 I&amp;rsquo;ve moved down from Imperial College London to Bath University, joining as a PostDoc on an EPSRC Programme Grant (&lt;a href=&#34;http://gow.epsrc.ac.uk/NGBOViewGrant.aspx?GrantRef=EP/K016288/1&#34;&gt;Energy Materials: Computational Solutions&lt;/a&gt;). Here, I am in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://people.bath.ac.uk/aw558/WMD&#34;&gt;Walsh Materials Design Group&lt;/a&gt; - still PhotoVoltaic based, but more concerned with Perovskites and &lt;a href=&#34;http://kesterite.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Kesterites&lt;/a&gt; than Fullerenes. Crystal structures have the most fantastic names - after the Georgian mineralogists who scurried the Earth&amp;rsquo;s crust looking for new ones and named them either after each other, or crazy portmanteaus of Greek &amp;amp; Latin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bath university is up a great big hill (well, not that big - only a 150 m climb!), which makes the cycle up in the morning a bit arduous, but the return home jet propelled. Much more staggering has been the culture shock of moving from The Big Smoke to a rather small (and seemingly smaller) British town. All the coffee shops close at 6PM, the city centre empties to leave a ghost town. But Bristol is just a short hop away by train, and seems to get nearly as many gigs as London, and being surrounded by hills and countryside is great for the cycling possibilities (and there&amp;rsquo;s an active cycling club in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vc-walcot.com/&#34;&gt;VC Walcot&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>